Hello and welcome to another computer
architecture CPU emulator walkthrough.
And so in this one we are going to go
through a number of simple samples. And
I will turn on the viewing of the assembly
language down here so we can see that. And
and so this this one here is really simple.
It is going to load a constant into the A
register
27. That's a decimal 27. And then we're
going to add 15. So this is going to be 27 +
15 and then
we're going to store it into memory location
0 0 and then we're going to stop. So this is
going to cause a little bit of output. So
let's go ahead and narrate the execution and
then start
it running. Let's put this in a place. Well,
we don't want to hide the memory because the
action
is going to happen here in the memory. So
here we go. PC0x 0. Load accumulator.
Immediate 0x1
B. PC0X02. Add with carry. Immediate 0x0F PC
0x04. Store accumulator to address 0 PC0X06.
Great printed output asterisk. So this time
we stored something in the memory. So the
the the
the program will dump the memory up to a
zero byte. like C, right? It'll dump the
memory up to a zero byte. And 0x2A, let's go
look at our ASCII chart. 0x2A 0x2A 0x2A,
there we go, is a 42 decimal. Interesting
choice of number. And it's an asterisk. And
so it's a 0x2A. You can see it in the
memory. And when the program stops, it
prints it out.
Okay. So then let's take a look at another
simple example. Let's take a look at the
assembly
language for it. So this is going to
basically stick that letter H into the into
the accumulator
then store it into lo memory location zero
and then put a I in the accumulator and
store that in
memory location one. So let's let's go ahead
and step that. PC0x 0 load accumulator
immediate 0x48.
I'll go to the next instruction which is
going to store that one.
And now we're going to load the I load
accumulator.
So 0x69 is the letter I. And now we're going
to store it. PC0x06. Store accumulator to
address
one. So this that we just put some some data
into memory location one. We're going
to step one more. It's going to stop and
it's going to print out what is here in ASI
PC08.
So it said hi. Okay. And so let's do one
more simple one. And this one's weird. So I
have a single instruction which is break
which is stop. And you'll notice it says
0000 right away. But I use the assembly
language data pseudo. We call these pseudo
ops. And it
preloads the data. And it says, and this is
hello world. So you can see it's hello world
in ASKI. 0x20 is the space. So we're just
going to run this, but it's going to
immediately stop,
but it's going to dump the memory because we
preloaded data into memory. And so this is
really showing you more about how this data
pseudo operation works. PC0X00 great printed
output. Hello world. Okay. And so let me
then show you one more thing in this. I want
to you
you can write code in the assembler. Okay.
So you this is a little text editor and is
you read the
assembly language. You go into the
documentation, read the assembly language
and then you can say
take this code and assemble it. So it
assembled it and so now it says hello CA for
E. So there's
the So in location five is the space and
then C is the 43. Let's go ahead and bring
up a ASKI
chart so we can figure out what this memory
location six is. It's a 0x43 and that's C.
And then 41 is the A. Right? So you can see
this. And now we're going to run it.
It's only got one instruction which is a
stop instruction but then it's going to
print out its
output hello. So so that was that's just
really showing you the the
data the data thing. So and we later we will
use this to preload data and
then write code that reads from memory and
does something to that memory. But for now,
I hope you found this walk through with a
couple of simple examples useful.